A Guide to the Papers of K. Edward Lay
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Dwellings-Other Counties
  - The Barn, Augusta County; Berry Hill, Petersburg, ca. 1800; Big Cobler Farm, Fauquier County; Boxwood Farm, Hot Springs, late 18th century; Broad Lawn, Hot Springs, Bath County, ca. 1890; Buckland Farm, Prince William County, ca. 1743; Cartersville Tavern, Cartersville, Cumberland County, ca. 18
    Rams Lake Farm, Spotsylvania County; Rapidan River Farm, Culpeper County; River Bend Farm, Warren County, ca. 1752; River Ridge Farm, Bath County, 1975; Snowden, Goochland County, ca. 1820; Spring Brook Farm, Somerset; Spring Lake Farms, Moneta; Stonegate Farm, Greenbrier County, 1957; Two Brooks Farm, Goshen, Rockbridge County, ca. 1880, ca. 1972; Upper Brandon, Prince George County, ca. 1790-1820; White Hall Plantation, Campbell County, ca. 1809; Wiloma Plantation, Botetourt County, ca. 1900; Windy Cove Farm, Bath County, ca. 1847; Woodlawn, Deep Run Hunt, Goochland County, ca. 1780; Woodlawn, Port Royal, ca. 1790, 1810-1830, 1850
- Barns-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Ben Coolyn Barn, (Fruitland; Tall Oaks), Keswick, mid 19th century 1978-1990 (Box 24)
  - Brown Barn, Browns Cove, early 18th century 1982-1995 (Box 24)
  - Carrsville Orchard Company Barn, 19th century 1995 (Box 24)
  - Castalia Barn, Cismont, 1929 1929-1995 (Box 24)
  - Enniscorthy Barn, Green Mountain, late 18th century 1995 (Box 24)
  - Ingleside Horse Barn, Garth Road, 1935 1993-1995 (Box 24)
  - Nydrie Stables, Green Mountain, ca. 1898, 1932 1995 (Box 24)
  - Page Brook Bank Barn, Albemarle 1991 (Box 24)
  - Redlands Barn 1995 (Box 24)
  - Senlis, (Fieldstone; Leigh Barn), Albemarle, ca. 1770 1976-1995 (Box 24)
  - Sherwood Barn n.d. (Box 24)
  - Stockton Creek Barn, Greenwood, late 19th century 1973-1995 (Box 24)
  - Sutherland Barn, Crossroads, Covesville, ca. 1810 1980 (Box 24)
  - Barns, General 1974-1996 (Box 24)
    Abell Place Tobacco Farm, near Ivy, 19th century; Auburn Hill Chicken Coop; Clover Fields Barn; Earlysville Barn; Ingleridge Horse Farm, Garth Road, early 20th century; Martin Barn, Dongegal, mid 19th century; Miller Place Barn, Free Union; Monacan, Ellerslie, Carters Bridge, ca. 1790; Underhill Tobacco Farm, Albemarle, 19th century; Wilhoit Barns, Nortonsville, early 19th century; Barnes in Albemarle County...
- Ecclesiastical-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Albemarle County Church Records 1983-2000 (Box 24)
  - Alberene Baptist Church, 1901-1903, 1971, 1976 1973 (Box 24)
  - All Saints Episcopal Church, Stony Point, 1926 1986 (Box 24)
  - All Saints Episcopal Chapel, White Hall, 1905 1934 (Box 24)
  - Ballenger Creek Church, (Ballinger Anglican Church site), 1746 1931, 1978 (Box 24)
  - Batesville United Methodist Church, 1860-1861, 1940s, 1953, 1970 1995 (Box 24)
  - Belmont Baptist Church, Monticello Avenue, 1958 1982 (Box 24)
  - Beth Israel Temple, E. Jefferson Street, 1882, 1904 moved 1994-1995 (Box 24)
  - Binghams Methodist Church, (Austin's Meeting House), Nortonsville, ca. 1795 1986-1988 (Box 24)
  - Blue Ridge Sanitarium Chapel, 20 South, 1925 1982 (Box 24)
  - Buck Island Methodist Church, (Buck Eyeland Church), 1890 1982-1995 (Box 24)
  - Buck Mountain Episcopal Church, (Buck Mountain Anglican Church), Earlysville, 1747, early 19th century, 1859 moved 1983-1999 (Box 24)
  - Centenary Methodist Church South, Covesville, 1840 1986-1995 (Box 24)
  - Charlottesville Christian Church, (First Christian Church), First and Market Streets, 1836 1981-1995 (Box 24)
  - Chestnut Grove Baptist Church, 1879, 1960, 1973 1973-1995 (Box 24)
  - Christ Church, (Christ Episcopal Church 1), Lot #66, Charlottesville, 1824-1826, 1895-1898 1989-1995 (Box 24)
  - Christ Episcopal Church 2, Lot #66, Charlottesville, 1895-1898 1986-1995 (Box 24)
  - Christ Episcopal Church Glendower, Keene, 1832, 1958, 1961 1957-1998 (Box 24)
  - Church of the Good Shepherd Episcopal Chapel, (Shepherd's Hill Chapel), 29 South, 1905 1982 (Box 24)
  - Church of Our Savior Episcopal Chapel, E. Rio Road, 1905-1906 1983 (Box 24)
  - Cove Presbyterian Church, Covesville, 1769 log, 1809 brick, ca. 1880 1975-1991 (Box 24)
  - Crozet United Methodist Church, 1889 1986 (Box 24)
  - Delevan Baptist Church, (First Baptist Church; "First Colored Baptist Church of Charlottesville; Mudwall Church; Black congregation), 1883 1993-1996 (Box 25)
  - Earlysville Union Church, (Baptist/Presbyterian/Methodist; Free Union Church), 1833 1993-1995 (Box 25)
  - Ebenezer Baptist Church, (Black Baptist Church), Sixth Street, 1894, 1908 n.d. (Box 25)
  - Edgehill Episcopal Chapel, Shadwell, 1875-1890 1995 (Box 25)
  - Emmanuel Episcopal Church, 250 West, 1862-1863, 1890, 1911-1914, 1930s, 1940s, 1960, 1983 1981-1991 (Box 25)
  - Evergreen Baptist Church, (Black Baptist Church), Proffit, ca. 1891, 1955, 1962 1986 (Box 25)
  - First Baptist Church 1, Second N. E. and E. Jefferson Streets, 1852 1982 (Box 25)
  - First Baptist Church, Second N. E. and E. Jefferson Streets, 1904 n.d. (Box 25)
  - First Methodist Church 3, First N. E. and Jefferson Streets, 1924, 1978 n.d. (Box 25)
  - First Presbyterian Church 1, Second and Market Streets, 1828 1987 (Box 25)
  - First Presbyterian Church 2, (YMCA; Bell sold to Mount Zion Church), S. E. Corner of Second and Market Streets, 1856 1992 (Box 25)
  - First Presbyterian Church 3, S. W. Corner of Second N. E. and Market Streets, 1898 n.d. (Box 25)
  - First Presbyterian Church 4, 500 Park Street, 1955 1995 (Box 25)
  - Free Union Baptist Church, 1837 1976-1995 (Box 25)
  - Friends' Meeting House, Sugar Loaf, 18th century n.d. (Box 25)
  - Glebe of Saint Anne's Episcopal Parish, Cismont, ca. 1765 1991-1994 (Box 25)
  - Grace Episcopal Church, (Walker's Parish), Cismont, 1847-1855, 1895 1984-1995 (Box 25)
  - High Street Baptist Church, N. W. Corner of High and 7th N. E. Streets, 1901 1995 (Box 25)
  - Hillsboro Baptist Church, Yancey Mills, 1905 1982-1995 (Box 25)
  - Holy Comforter Catholic Church, 210 E. Jefferson Street, 1880, 1925 1995 (Box 25)
  - Howardsville Methodist Church, 1854 1988-1995 (Box 25)
  - Lebanon Presbyterian Church, Route 796 off 250 West, ca. 1850-1880 1983-1991 (Box 25)
  - Liberty Baptist Church, (mission of Preddy's Creek Baptist Church, Eastham, 1829 1979 (Box 25)
  - Maple Grove Disciples of Christ Church, Proffit, 1912 1986 (Box 25)
  - Mayo Chapel, Alberene, ca. 1860 1979 (Box 25)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church 1, S. E. Corner of Water and 2nd Streets, 1834 1995 (Box 25)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church 2, S. W. Corner of Water and 1st Streets, 1859, 1889 1980-1995 (Box 25)
  - Mount Calvary Baptist Church, (black congregation), Ivy, ca. 1890 1976-1995 (Box 25)
  - Mount Ed Baptist Church, (Whitesides), Batesville, 1788, 1856-1857 1988-1991 (Box 25)
  - Mount Moriah Methodist Church, (Maupin's Meeting House), White Hall, 1788, 1834, 1854, 1913 1976-1995 (Box 25)
  - Mount Sinai Baptist Church, (back congregation), Earlysville, late 19th century 1986-1995 (Box 25)
  - Mount Zion Baptist Church, (1st African Church; black congregation), 105 Ridge Street, 1878 1991-1996 (Box 25)
  - Mountain Plains Presbyterian Church, Crozet, ca. 1855, 1959 1976-1995 (Box 25)
  - Neve Hall Manse, (Diocesan Missionary Society of Virginia), South Albemarle, 1924 n.d. (Box 25)
  - Oak Union Baptist Church, (black congregation), Owensville, 1880 1986 (Box 25)
  - Parsonage, Scottsville, 1895 n.d. (Box 25)
  - Preddy's Creek Baptist Church, Stony Points, ca. 1800 1973-1978 (Box 25)
  - Rectory, (Christ Church Glendower Episcopal Rectory), Keene, 1787, ca. 1839 1977-1990 (Box 25)
  - Rising Sun Baptist Church, South Garden, 1901 1986 (Box 25)
  - St. James Episcopal Church, (Garth Road Chapel), Owensville, ca. 1896 1986 (Box 25)
  - St. John's Episcopal Church, Scottsville, 1875, 1949 n.d. (Box 25)
  - St. Luke's Episcopal Chapel, Simeon, 1892 1983-1992 (Box 25)
  - St. Paul's Episcopal Church, (St. Paul's Memorial Church, University Avenue, 1910, 1925, 1958) n.d. (Box 25)
  - St. Paul's Episcopal Church, Ivy, 1869-1870 1976-1999 (Box 25)
  - St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, Esmont, 1914 1986 (Box 25)
  - Sand Road Baptist Church, Alberene, post 1883 n.d. (Box 25)
  - Scottsville Baptist Church, 1840 1978-1995 (Box 26)
  - Scottsville Disciples of Christ Church, 1846 1975-1995 (Box 26)
  - Scottsville Presbyterian Church, ca. 1832 1983 (Box 26)
  - Slate Hill Baptist Church, Simeon, mid 19th century 1977 (Box 26)
  - South Plains Presbyterian Church, Simeon near Keswick, ca. 1828 1983-1994 (Box 26)
  - Spruce Hill Rectory, Cismont, ca. 1930 1993-1996 (Box 26)
  - Tabor Presbyterian Church, Crozet, 1915 1982-1983 (Box 26)
  - Trinity Episcopal Church, (Church of the Ascension; black congregation), 10th and Preston Avenue, 1910 1973-1986 (Box 26)
  - Trinity Episcopal Church, (Crossroads School House), 1835 1980 (Box 26)
  - Union Ridge Baptist Church, 743 Hydraulic Road, ca. 1900 1986-1995 (Box 26)
  - Unitarian Church, Rugby Road, mid 20th century 1995 (Box 26)
  - University Baptist Church, 1223 W. Main Street, ca. 1900 1975-1995 (Box 26)
  - University of Virginia Chapel, 1885-1890 1992-1995 (Box 26)
  - Wesley Methodist Chapel, (Wesley Chapel United Methodist Church), Free Union, 1833 1986-1988 (Box 26)
  - Westminster Presbyterian Church, 190 Rugby Road, 1939 n.d. (Box 26)
  - Woolen Mills Chapel, (Union Chapel; Calvary Baptist Church), 1819 E. Market Street, 1887, 1908 1986 (Box 26)
  - Zion Baptist Church, (black congregation), Crossroads, 1871 1994 (Box 26)
  - Churches, General 1978-1997 (Box 26)
    Albemarle House Chapel, 1980s; A. M. E. (Black Moth) Church, Charlottesville, late 19th century; Batesville Methodist Parsonage, Covesville, 1872-1873, ca. 1910; Bethany Baptist Church, 1875; Bethel Baptist Church, (Bethlehem Apostalic Church; Bethel Baptist Institutional Church), Charlottesville, 1922; Boonesville Church; Browns Cove United Methodist Church, (Cove Chapel), 1895
    Charlottesville Lutheran Church; Christian Science Church, Charlottesville, 1958-1959; East Streak Episcopal Church, Howardsville; Episcopal Manse, (The Old Manse), Charlottesville, 1839; Ivy Creek Methodist Church, 1926; Ivy Parish Rectory, Verdant Lawn, 1865, ca. 1910; Jarman Gap Presbyterian Church, ca. 1890-1920; Jessup Baptist Parsonage, Charlottesville, ca. 1885
    Meadland, (Reverend Richard K. Meade Home; Llewellyn; Episcopal Manse; Dr. Charles H. Hedges Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1844; Methodist Presiding Elder's House, Charlottesville, ca. 1891; Milton Church, late 18th century; Mount Carmel Church, Browns Cove; Mount Eagle Baptist Church, Simeon, ca. 1912; Mount Salem Church, Crozet, ca. 1920-1940; Mount Zion Baptist Church, Earlysville, ca. 1870; Mt. Zion United Methodist Church, Esmont, ca. 1900; Mountain Chapel Methodist, Earlysville, 1917; Mountain View Baptist Church, Covesville, 1907-1909
    New Hope Baptist Church, Esmont, early 20th century; The Old Manse, Charlottesville, 1839, 1930s; Olivet Presbyterian Church, Garth Road, ca. 1880; Park Hill Parsonage, First Baptist Church of Charlottesville Parsonage, early 20th century; Parson's Green, Charlottesville, 18th century; Piedmont Christian Church, Keswick, 1879; Rose Hill Baptist Church, Simeon, late 19th century; Scottsville Methodist Church Parsonage, 1832; St. John the Baptist Episcopal Church, Crozet, ca. 1920; St. John's Baptist Church, Cobham, ca. 1881; Sharon Church; Temple Hill Methodist Church site, ca. 1820; Union Grove Baptist Church, Keswick, ca. 1886; Wake Forest Baptist Church, Simeon, ca. 1971; Zion Hill Baptist Church, Cismont, ca. 1890
- Depots-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Alberene Depot 1995 (Box 26)
  - Arrowhead Depots n.d. (Box 26)
  - Charlottesville Chesapeake & Ohio Depot, ca. 1905 1987-1995 (Box 26)
  - Charlottesville Southern Depot, 1885, 1913 1991-1995 (Box 26)
  - Cobham Depot, 1860, 1987 1970-1987 (Box 26)
  - Crozet Depot n.d. (Box 26)
  - Esmont Depot n.d. (Box 26)
  - Greenwood Depot n.d. (Box 26)
  - Howardsville Depot n.d. (Box 26)
  - Ivy Depot, ca. 1851 1960-1976 (Box 26)
  - Keswick Depot, ca. 1850 1978-1994 (Box 26)
  - Lindsay Depot 1995 (Box 26)
  - North Garden Depot, 1916, 1923 n.d. (Box 26)
  - Rail Road Tunnels, 1856 1976-1996 (Box 26)
  - Rose Cottage (Station Master's House), 1856, 1900, 1910 1990-1995 (Box 26)
  - Scottsville Depot, ca. 1860 1978 (Box 26)
  - Shadwell Depot, 1915 1975-1976 (Box 27)
  - Warren Depot, ca. 1900 1973-1996 (Box 27)
  - Depots, General n.d. (Box 27)
- Mills-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Advance Mills, (Frays Mill; Freys Mill), Lynch River 1994 (Box 27)
  - Mills-"B": Ballard's Mill, Moorman's River, Millington; Bowen's Mill site, (Ramsay's Mill), Stockton's Creek; Bowen's Mill House, Albemarle; Brockman's Mill, Priddy's Creek; Brown's Mill, Mount Fair; Buck Island Mill site, (Buckeyeland Mill; Flanagan's Mill), Buck Island Creek; Burnt Mills, (Rivanna Mill; Edward Ferneyhough Mill), Rivanna River 1976-1982 (Box 27)
  - Cochran's Millhouse, Meadow Creek 1992 (Box 27)
  - Crossroad's Mill, North Garden 1980-1999 (Box 27)
  - Mills-"C": Campbell's Mill, Albemarle; Crozet Mill 1995 (Box 27)
  - Dawson's Mill, Ballenger Creek 1995 (Box 27)
  - Dwyer's Mill and Millhouse, Totier Creek 1978-1997 (Box 27)
  - Eolus' Mill, Carter's Bridge 1970-2000 (Box 27)
  - Mills-"F"-"H": Flanagan's Mill, Albemarle; Gilmer's Mill, Simeon; Hardware River Mill ruins, Albemarle; Harris' Mill, Albemarle; Hartman's Mill, Charlottesville 1982-1995 (Box 27)
  - Harris Mill, Slate Quarry Creek 1995 (Box 27)
  - Hatton Grange Mill, James River 1996 (Box 27)
  - Hydraulic Millhouse, Rivanna River n.d. (Box 27)
  - Ivy Mill, Ivy Creek 1976-1995 (Box 27)
  - Jarman-Harris Millhouse, Mechums River 1976-1995 (Box 27)
  - Jefferson Mill (Peter), Shadwell on Rivanna River 1976-1993 (Box 27)
  - Jefferson Mill (Peter Field), Hardware River 1973-1995 (Box 27)
  - Mills-"J" - "K": Jones Mill site, Beaver Creek; Kinkead's Mill, Stockton's Creek; n.d. (Box 27)
  - Maupin Millhouse, Whitehall on Moorman's River 1955-1990 (Box 27)
  - Meadow Run Mill, Michie Tavern 1976-1995 (Box 27)
  - Merrie Mill, (Merry Mill; Grist Mill; Walker Mill), Cismont 1978-1995 (Box 27)
  - Mills-"M": Maury's Mill, Moore's Creek; Minor Mill, Red Buck Creek; Monroe Hill; Moore's Creek Mill; Mount Fair Gristmill 1978-1995 (Box 27)
  - Pace's Mill, Mechums River 1994 (Box 27)
  - Rio Mills, (William Meriwether Mill; Nathaniel Burnley's Mill), Rivanna River 1995 (Box 27)
  - Stockton Creek Mill, Yancey Mills 1990-1995 (Box 27)
  - Mills-"S": Saw Mill; Scottsville Grist Mill, (Scottsville Flour Mill); Secretary's Mill, Hardware River; Simms' Mill, Priddy's Creek; Suddarth's Mill, Hardware River 1995 (Box 27)
  - Tsuquatantia Millhouse, (Cocke's Mill; Cole's Mill; Johnson's Mill; Green Mountain Mill), North Garden on Hardware River 1978-1995 (Box 27)
  - Walker Mill and Millhouse, (Cowherd's Mill; Carver's Mill; Windsor Mill), Happy Creek/Howard's Creek 1978-1997 (Box 27)
  - Warren Mill, (Staple's Mill), Ballenger Creek 1977-1998 (Box 27)
  - Woods Mill, (Smith's Mill; Durett's Mill), Hardware River 1995 (Box 27)
  - Woolen Mills, (Marchant's Mill), Rivanna River, Charlottesville 1975-1887 (Box 27)
  - Mills-"W": James Walker's Mill; Wilhoit Mill Farm, Free Union; Wrenn's Mill n.d. (Box 27)
  - Yancey's Mill, Crozet on Stockton's Creek 1994 (Box 27)
  - Mills, General 1950-1998 (Box 27)
- Schools-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Albemarle County Schools; Albemarle College, Charlottesville 1955-1999 (Box 28)
  - Batesville Elementary School; Batesville School n.d. (Box 28)
  - Buck Island School n.d. (Box 28)
  - Schools-"B" - "C": Burnley School; Carr and Maury School; Cismont School; Covesville School; Crozet School 1995 (Box 28)
  - Clark Elementary School, Belmont 1981-1995 (Box 28)
  - Ecole, Batesville 1975-1998 (Box 28)
  - Esmont High School n.d. (Box 28)
  - Schools-"E" - "H": Earlysville High School; Glendower School; Greenwood School for Boys; Hickory Stick, Farmington Hunt; Howardsville School 1976-1995 (Box 28)
  - Jefferson School for Boys, Charlottesville 1995 (Box 28)
  - Schools-"J" - "L": Jefferson High School, Charlottesville; Major Jones School for Boys; Charlottesville; Lane High School, Charlottesville; Liberty School, Eastham 1995-1999 (Box 28)
  - Maury Classical School, (Maury Anglican Classical School; Glebe of Fredericksville Parish; William Fitzhugh Gordon Home; Reverend Matthew Maury School), Edgeworth 1995 (Box 28)
  - McGuffey Elementary School, Charlottesville n.d. (Box 28)
  - Midway School, Charlottesville 1995 (Box 28)
  - Miller School, (Miller Manual Labor School), near Batesville 1972-1996 (Box 28)
  - Schools-"M" - "P": McIntire High School, Charlottesville; Mount Alto School; Newtown School, (Newtown Community Center), Albemarle; North Garden Elementary School; Nortonsville School; Piedmont Female Academy, Cobham; Proffit School 1995 (Box 28)
  - Rio School, Greenbrier, Charlottesville 1993-1995 (Box 28)
  - Rockland Home School for Girls and Young Ladies, Albemarle n.d. (Box 28)
  - Schools-"R" - "W": Rawlings Institute, (Albemarle Female Institute; St. Anne's School Old Main, Charlottesville; Red Hill School; Rockfield School, (Gentry Ray House), Ragged Mountain; Rose Hill School, Albemarle; School House, Albemarle; Scottsville High School; Colonel Watson School for Boys, Charlottesville 1978-1995 (Box 28)
  - Venable Elementary School, Charlottesville 1981-1995 (Box 28)
- Shops and Stores-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Anderson Brother's Bookstore 1996-1998 (Box 28)
  - Bishop's Store, 1931 1995 (Box 28)
  - Blackwell's Store n.d. (Box 28)
  - Carters Bridge Store, 19th century 1995 (Box 28)
  - Charlottesville Hardware Store, 1895, ca. 1975 1975-1989 (Box 28)
  - Covesville Store 1993-1995 (Box 28)
  - Crossroad's Store, early 20th century n.d. (Box 28)
  - Davis Store 1995 (Box 28)
  - Estes (R. N.) Store, 1890s, 1933 1985-1995 (Box 28)
  - Foster-Layman Store 1995 (Box 28)
  - Harris Shop 1976 (Box 28)
  - Hatton Store, 1870s 1996 (Box 28)
  - Heards Store, ca. 1900 1993-1995 (Box 28)
  - Ivy Stores, ca. 1850, ca. 1895 1995 (Box 28)
  - Keene Store 1995 (Box 28)
  - Lane Store 1996 (Box 28)
  - Marshall-Parrish Store, late 19th century, 1917 1982-1995 (Box 28)
  - Maupin Store n.d. (Box 28)
  - Maupin (J. J.) Store, ca.1890, 1973 n.d. (Box 28)
  - McKee Block, early 19th century 1991 (Box 28)
  - Monroe Hill Law Office, ca. 1789 1981 (Box 28)
  - Monticello Bank n.d. (Box 28)
  - Number Nothing Shops, ca. 1820 1980-1995 (Box 28)
  - Piedmont Store 1976 (Box 28)
  - Powells Stores, early 20th century 1995 (Box 28)
  - Purvis Store, early 20th century 1993 (Box 28)
  - Sinclair Store 1979 (Box 28)
  - Thompson Store 1982 (Box 28)
  - Warren Store, ca. 1855 1962-1995 (Box 28)
  - Wyant Store, 1913 1963-1995 (Box 28)
  - Stores-Miscellaneous: Advance Mills Store; Barracks Road; Allen Store and Woody Dance Hall, Simeon, 1920s; Baber's Store & Post Office, Howardsville, 1880s; Batesville Blacksmith Shop, late 19th century; Belmont Store; Cigar Factory; Old Cobham Store; Craig's Store; Earlysville Store; Greenwood Brick Store; Keswick Store; Nortonsville Store; Steed's Store; Stony Point Country Store; Tapscott Store; Wagner's Store; William Walker Store; W. W. Wood Store; Wood's Store; Lot #55 shop 1993-1998 (Box 28)
- Taverns, Inns, and Hotels-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Albemarle Hotel 1975-1999 (Box 29)
  - Black's Tavern 1986-1995 (Box 29)
  - Blue Ridge Terrace Inn n.d. (Box 29)
  - Boar's Head Inn 1999 (Box 29)
  - Boyd's Tavern 1976-1996 (Box 29)
  - Brooksville Tavern 1989-1996 (Box 29)
  - Burnley's Tavern 1974-1995 (Box 29)
  - Castiglione Tavern 1936-1993 (Box 29)
  - Central Hotel n.d. (Box 29)
  - Clarksville Tavern n.d. (Box 29)
  - Crossroads Tavern 1980-1993 (Box 29)
  - D. S. Tavern 1976-1983 (Box 29)
  - Eagle Tavern, ca. 1791 1978-1991 (Box 29)
  - Farish House n.d. (Box 29)
  - Farmers' Hotel 1999 (Box 29)
  - Fretwell-Tillman Tavern, ca. 1810, 1820s, ca. 1835 1989-1992 (Box 29)
  - Fry's Spring Hotel 1982-1991 (Box 29)
  - Garland's Tavern 1992 (Box 29)
  - Garth Tavern 1982-1992 (Box 29)
  - Green Teapot Inn 1976-1995 (Box 29)
  - Hardin's Tavern (Hardendale) 1995-1999 (Box 29)
  - Jefferson Hotel 1990-1995 (Box 29)
  - La Fourche Tavern 1976-1995 (Box 29)
  - Leake's Tavern, 1770 1995-1996 (Box 29)
  - Locust Grove Tavern 1976-2000 (Box 29)
  - Locustdale Inn 1990-1996 (Box 29)
  - Long House (May's Tavern) 1955-1995 (Box 29)
  - Michie Tavern 1928-1997 (Box 30)
  - Monticello Hotel 1974-1993 (Box 30)
  - Oak Grove Tavern n.d. (Box 30)
  - Pinch 'Em Slyly Tavern 1978 (Box 30)
  - Price's Hotel 1976-1995 (Box 30)
  - Queen Charlotte Hotel 1995 (Box 30)
  - Scottsville Tavern 1995 (Box 30)
  - Swan Tavern n.d. (Box 30)
  - Terrell's Ordinary n.d. (Box 30)
  - Thomas Jefferson Inn 1995 (Box 30)
  - Town and Country Motor Lodge 1998 (Box 30)
  - Traveler's Grove Tavern n.d. (Box 30)
  - Warren Tavern 1992-1996 (Box 30)
  - White Hall Inn 1976-1995 (Box 30)
  - Woodstock Hall Tavern 1978-1996 (Box 30)
  - Woolen Mills Tavern 1976 (Box 30)
  - Yancey's Tavern 1990-1995 (Box 30)
  - Taverns and Inns - Miscellaneous: Alphin Hostelry; Bentivoglio Tavern; Bowcock Tavern; Bramham's Tavern; Cabell House; Carlton House Hotel; Dolley Madison Inn; Eubank's Tavern; Field Public House; Fitz' Tavern; Hocker's Tavern; Old Howardsville Tavern; Oak Grove Tavern; The Ordinary; Pleasant Grove Tavern; Queen Charlotte Hotel; Terrell's Ordinary; Thomas Jefferson Inn; Travelers' Grove Tavern; Walker's Tavern; "Taverns-Charlottesville and Albemarle County, Virginia, 1810-1860" 1950-1995 (Box 30)
- Commercial Buildings
  - Commercial Buildings-Banks: Citizens Bank and Trust Company; Bank of Crozet, 1905; Esmont National Bank Building, (Post Office), 1902; Howardsville Bank, ca. 1835; Jefferson National Bank, (Leterman/Jefferson National Bank Building), 1899, 1911; Monticello Bank, 1853, 1854; National Bank and Trust, (Jefferson National Bank), 1914, 1920; Peoples National Bank, (Timberlakes Drugstore), 1896, ca. 1909, 1917, ca. 1950; Peoples National Bank, (Sovran Bank, Virginia National Bank), 1916; 1929; 1956; Lot #55 Bank; "Charlottesville Banks before 1935" 1979-1995 (Box 30)
  - Commercial Buildings-Hospitals and Sanitariums: Blue Ridge Sanitarium, Route 20 S., 1914, 1919; Elderly Ladies Home; Magruder Sanitarium, W. Jefferson Street, 1899; Martha Jefferson Hospital, (Martha Jefferson Sanitarium), E. High Street, 1903, razed 1929, 1976; Minor-Nelson Sanitarium, (Nelson Sanitarium; Stedman House; Charles Minor Home; R. B. Nelson Home), E. High Street, ca. 1835, 1894 1980-1995 (Box 30)
  - Commercial Buildings-Law Offices: Limestone Law Office, 1794; Monroe Hill Law Office, ca. 1789 1981 (Box 30)
  - Commercial Buildings-Livery Stables: Carver's Livery Stable, W. Main Street, 19th century; Davis & Wood Livery, Fifth and Market Streets; 1910; Flannagan and Allegree's Stable, E. Market Street, 1905; Irving's Livery, E. Main Street, 19th century; Old Brick Stable, (Michie Company), E. Market Street, 1870s, 1896; Payne's Palace Stables, W. Main Street, 19th century; Railway Company Stables and Car Shed, (Charlottesville and University Street Railway Company Stables and Car Shed), E. Main Street, 1887, 1930 1979-1995 (Box 30)
  - Commercial Buildings-Lodges and Clubs: Alberene Masonic Lodge, 1900-1925; Elks Lodge, (Elk's Lodge Home; Juvenile Court), E. High Street, 1902-1903, burned late 1940s; Fry's Springs Clubhouse, (Wonderland), 1890, 1906, 1913, ca. 1928; Howardsville Masonic Lodge, (George Lodge 32), 1846; Keswick Hunt Club, 1898; Yancey Mills Masonic Lodge, Crozet, ca. 1910 1995 (Box 30)